<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="about_doc">
  <title>About this Document</title>
  
  <para>This document is designed to acquaint new users with the capabilities of the Pegasus Workflow Management System (WMS)
  and to demonstrate how WMS can efficiently provide a variety of ways to execute complex workflows on distributed resources.

  Readers are encouraged to take the walkthrough to acquaint themselves with the components of the Pegasus System.  Readers may also want to navigate through the chapters
  to acquaint themselves with the components on a deeper level to understand how to integrate Pegasus with your own data resources to resolve
  your individual computational challenges.</para>
  
  <para/>
  
      
      <itemizedlist>
      
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>System Walkthrough</emphasis></para>
        <para>We walk you through a representative workflow project that includes all aspects of the Pegasus WMS. The project we use is is at a level of complexity
        that is needed for the vast majority of users. Within the text there are links to advanced concepts and structures shoud the need arise to explore them.</para>
      </listitem>
      
       <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Workflows</emphasis></para>
        <para>An introducion to the concepts of workflows, the types of workflows, and how they are used in the Pegasus system</para>
      </listitem>

      
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Pegasus Components</emphasis></para>
        <para>An introduction to the components of the Pegasus Workflow Management System (WMS)</para>
      </listitem>


      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Catalog Details</emphasis></para>
        <para>Detailed information about catalog implementation requirements and settings</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Planning and Submitting</emphasis></para>
        <para> How to plan a DAX (abstract) workflow and submit it to the DAG to
         create an executable workflow. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Monitoring Workflows</emphasis></para>
        <para> How to monitor, debug, and view statistics about the execution of the workflow  </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Example Workflows</emphasis></para>
        <para> Example workflows are included to assist users with becoming familiar with existing workflows to gain insight into creating their own  </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Advanced Concepts and Configurations</emphasis></para>
        <para> Advanced information section of several chapters with configuration details for use in designing advanced workflows for very large scale projects</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>API Reference</emphasis></para>
        <para> View API details</para>
      </listitem>
          <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Command Reference</emphasis></para>
        <para> View a listing of all commands avaialble in the Pegasus WMS</para>
      </listitem>
      
          <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Useful Tips</emphasis></para>
        <para> View useful tips and best practices.</para>
      </listitem>
      
          <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Installation</emphasis></para>
        <para> View complete installation steps for the range of installations available with Pegasus WMS.</para>
      </listitem>
          <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Migrating from Version 2.x</emphasis></para>
        <para> View instructions for upgrading a Pegasus version2.x installation to version 3.0.</para>
      </listitem>
      
          <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Glossary</emphasis></para>
        <para> View a glossary of terms and concepts referenced in Pegasus WMS</para>
      </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</chapter>












