<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="configuration">
   <title>Pegasus Configuration</title>
   <section>
       <title>Introduction</title>
       <para>...</para>
   </section>
   <section>
       <title>Properties</title>

    <para>Properties allow you to configure Pegasus in various ways by selection
    various catalog implementations, enabling and disabling various features or
    just additionally tuning them. Pegasus utilizes Java properties technology.
    Pegasus properties can be defined in several ways</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>System Property File - Found in $PEGASUS_HOME/etc/properties.
        Lowest Priority</para>

        <para>These properties are generally set by the administrator to be
        shared by all users of the installation. They default location of
        $PEGASUS_HOME/etc/properties can be overridden by using the property
        pegasus.system.properties=&lt;path to a file&gt; on the command line or
        in the user properties file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>User Property File - Found in the $HOME/.pegasusrc. Higher
        Priority</para>

        <para>Thse properties are generally set by a user to augment existing
        properties from the system property file or override a few setting. The
        default location of $HOME/.pegasusrc can be overridden by using the
        property pegasus.user.properties on the command line or in the system
        property file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Command Line Properties - Provided on the command line of any
        Pegasus executable. Highest Priority</para>

        <para>The command line properties are specified on the command line of
        any Pegasus clients by using -D&lt;property&gt;=&lt;value&gt;. These
        properties need to be defined before any arguments to the
        clients.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> There is no space between
        -D and the property name</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>There is a priority to the order of reading and evaluating properties
    from these sources. The properties in the system file have the lowest
    priority, user properties override system properties and command line
    properties have the highest priority. Note that the values rely on proper
    capitalization, unless explicitly noted otherwise. Some properties if not
    specified may have default values. You can use variable substitution to use
    the value of one property in a second property. For instance,
    ${pegasus.home} means that the value depends on the value of the
    pegasus.home property plus any noted additions. You can use this notation to
    refer to other properties, though the extent of the substitutions are
    limited. Usually, you want to refer to a set of the standard system
    properties. Nesting is not allowed. Substitutions will only be done
    once.</para>

    <para>If you are in doubt which properties are actually visible, a sample
    application called show-properties dumps all properties after reading and
    prioritizing them.</para>

    <para>For running the above example we shall create a user properties file
    in $HOME/.pegasusrc and specify properties for Pegasus to find various
    catalogs</para>
    <programlisting><emphasis>$ vim $HOME/.pegasusrc</emphasis>


pegasus.catalog.replica=SimpleFile
pegasus.catalog.replica.file=$HOME/rc
pegasus.catalog.site=XML
pegasus.catalog.site.file=$HOME/sites.xml
pegasus.catalog.transformation=File
pegasus.catalog.transformation.file=$HOME/tc
pegasus.catalog.transformation.mapper=Staged
pegasus.dir.storage=pegasusstorage
pegasus.dir.exec=pegasusexec
pegasus.exitcode.scope=all</programlisting>

    <para>Substitute all $HOME and $USER variables above with actual values for
    your site.</para>

    <para>For a complete list of Pegasus properties refer to the properties.pdf
    in $PEGASUS_HOME/doc or on the Pegasus webiste at
    http://pegasus.isi.edu/doc.php</para>


PHP_BASIC_PROPERTIES

   </section>
</chapter>

