<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="about">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section id="overview">
    <title>Overview and Features</title>

    <para><ulink url="http://pegasus.isi.edu">Pegasus WMS</ulink> is a
    configurable system for mapping and executing abstract application
    workflows over a wide range of execution environments including a laptop, a
    campus cluster, a Grid, or a commercial or academic cloud. Today, Pegasus
    runs workflows on Amazon EC2, Nimbus, Open Science Grid, the TeraGrid, and
    many campus clusters. One workflow can run on a single system or across a
    heterogeneous set of resources. Pegasus can run workflows ranging from
    just a few computational tasks up to 1 million.</para>

    <para>Pegasus WMS bridges the scientific domain and the execution
    environment by automatically mapping high-level workflow descriptions onto
    distributed resources. It automatically locates the necessary input data
    and computational resources necessary for workflow execution. Pegasus
    enables scientists to construct workflows in abstract terms without
    worrying about the details of the underlying execution environment or the
    particulars of the low-level specifications required by the middleware
    (Condor, Globus, or Amazon EC2). Pegasus WMS also bridges the current
    cyberinfrastructure by effectively coordinating multiple distributed
    resources. The input to Pegasus is a description of the abstract workflow
    in XML format.</para>

    <para>Pegasus allows researchers to translate complex computational tasks
    into workflows that link and manage ensembles of dependent tasks and
    related data files. Pegasus automatically chains dependent tasks together,
    so that a single scientist can complete complex computations that once
    required many different people. New users are encouraged to explore the
    <link linkend="tutorial">tutorial chapter</link> to become
    familiar with how to operate Pegasus for their own workflows. Users create
    and run a sample project to demonstrate Pegasus capabilities. Users can
    also browse the <link linkend="useful_tips">Useful Tips</link> chapter to
    aid them in designing their workflows.</para>

    <para>Pegasus has a number of features that contribute to its useability
    and effectiveness.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Portability / Reuse</emphasis></para>

        <para>User created workflows can easily be run in different
        environments without alteration. Pegasus currently runs workflows on
        top of Condor, Grid infrastrucutures such as Open Science Grid and
        TeraGrid, Amazon EC2, Nimbus, and many campus clusters. The same
        workflow can run on a single system or across a heterogeneous set of
        resources.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Performance</emphasis></para>

        <para>The Pegasus mapper can reorder, group, and prioritize tasks in
        order to increase the overall workflow performance.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Scalability</emphasis></para>

        <para>Pegasus can easily scale both the size of the workflow, and the
        resources that the workflow is distributed over. Pegasus runs
        workflows ranging from just a few computational tasks up to 1 million.
        The number of resources involved in executing a workflow can scale as
        needed without any impediments to performance.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Provenance</emphasis></para>

        <para>By default, all jobs in Pegasus are launched via the <emphasis
        role="bold">kickstart</emphasis> process that captures runtime
        provenance of the job and helps in debugging. The provenance data is
        collected in a database, and the data can be summarised with tools such
        as <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-statistics</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">pegasus-plots</emphasis>, or directly with SQL
        queries.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Management</emphasis></para>

        <para>Pegasus handles replica selection, data transfers and output
        registrations in data catalogs. These tasks are added to a workflow as
        auxilliary jobs by the Pegasus planner.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Reliability</emphasis></para>

        <para>Jobs and data transfers are automatically retried in case of
        failures. Debugging tools such as <emphasis
        role="bold">pegasus-analyzer</emphasis> helps the user to debug the
        workflow in case of non-recoverable failures.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Error Recovery</emphasis></para>

        <para>When errors occur, Pegasus tries to recover when possible by
        retrying tasks, by retrying the entire workflow, by providing
        workflow-level checkpointing, by re-mapping portions of the workflow,
        by trying alternative data sources for staging data, and, when all
        else fails, by providing a rescue workflow containing a description of
        only the work that remains to be done. It cleans up storage as the
        workflow is executed so that data-intensive workflows have enough
        space to execute on storage-constrained resource. Pegasus keeps track
        of what has been done (provenance) including the locations of data
        used and produced, and which software was used with which
        parameters.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Operating Environments</emphasis></para>

        <para>Pegasus workflows can be deployed across a variety of
        environments:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Local Execution</emphasis></para>

            <para>Pegasus can run a workflow on a single computer with
            Internet access. Running in a local environment is quicker to
            deploy as the user does not need to gain access to muliple
            resources in order to execute a workfow.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Condor Pools and Glideins</emphasis></para>

            <para>Condor is a specialized workload management system for
            compute-intensive jobs. Condor queues workflows, schedules, and
            monitors the execution of each workflow. Condor Pools and Glideins
            are tools for submitting and executing the Condor daemons on a
            Globus resource. As long as the daemons continue to run, the
            remote machine running them appears as part of your Condor pool.
            For a more complete description of Condor, see the <ulink
            url="http://www.cs.wisc.edu/condor/description.html">Condor
            Project Pages </ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Grids</emphasis></para>

            <para>Pegasus WMS is entirely compatible with Grid computing. Grid
            computing relies on the concept of distributed computations.
            Pegasus apportions pieces of a workflow to run on distributed
            resources.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Clouds</emphasis></para>

            <para>Cloud computing uses a network as a means to connect a
            Pegasus end user to distributed resources that are based in the
            cloud.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="workflow_gallery">
    <title>Workflow Gallery</title>

    <para>Pegasus is curently being used in a broad range of applications. To
    review example workflows, see the <link
    linkend="example_workflows">Example Workflows</link> chapter. To see
    additional details about the workflows of the applications see the <ulink
    url="http://pegasus.isi.edu/workflow_gallery/">Gallery of
    Workflows</ulink>.</para>

    <para>We are always looking for new applications willing to leverage our
    workflow technologies. If you are interested please contact us at pegasus
    at isi dot edu.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="about_document">
    <title>About this Document</title>

    <para>This document is designed to acquaint new users with the
    capabilities of the Pegasus Workflow Management System (WMS) and to
    demonstrate how WMS can efficiently provide a variety of ways to execute
    complex workflows on distributed resources. Readers are encouraged to take
    the tutorial to acquaint themselves with the components of the Pegasus
    System. Readers may also want to navigate through the chapters to acquaint
    themselves with the components on a deeper level to understand how to
    integrate Pegasus with your own data resources to resolve your individual
    computational challenges.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="document_formats">
    <title>Document Formats (Web, PDF)</title>
    <para>The main version of this document is intended to be viewed online
    at the <ulink url="https://pegasus.isi.edu/documentation/">Pegasus website</ulink>. For
    offline viewing, a <ulink url="https://pegasus.isi.edu/documentation/pegasus-user-guide.pdf">PDF version</ulink>
    is also provided.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
