<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary version="5.0" xml:id="glossary" xml:lang=""
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <glossdiv>
    <title>A</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Abstract Workflow</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See DAX</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>C</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Concrete Workflow</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See Executable Workflow</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Condor-G</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A task broker that manages jobs to run at various distributed
        sites, using Globus GRAM to launch jobs on the remote
        sites.http://cs.wisc.edu/condor</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Clustering</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The process of clustering short running jobs together into a
        larger job. This is done to minimize the scheduling overhead for the
        jobs. The scheduling overhead is only incurred for the clustered job.
        For example if scheduling overhead is x seconds and 10 jobs are
        clustered into a larger job, the scheduling overhead for 10 jobs will
        be x instead of 10x.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>D</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>DAGMan</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The workflow execution engine used by Pegasus.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG)</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A graph in which all the arcs (connections) are unidirectional,
        and which has no loops (cycles).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>DAX</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The workflow input in XML format given to Pegasus in which
        transformations and files are represented as logical names. It is an
        execution-independent specification of computations</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Deferred Planning</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Planning mode to set up Pegasus. In this mode, instead of
        mapping the job at submit time, the decision of mapping a job to a
        site is deferred till a later point, when the job is about to be run
        or near to run.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>E</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Executable Workflow</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A workflow automatically genetared by Pegasus in which files are
        represented by physical filenames, and in which sites or hosts have
        been selected for running each task.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>F</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Full Ahead Planning</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Planning mode to set up Pegasus. In this mode, all the jobs are
        mapped before submitting the workflow for execution to the
        grid.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>G</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Globus</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The Globus Alliance is a community of organizations and
        individuals developing fundamental technologies behind the "Grid,"
        which lets people share computing power, databases, instruments, and
        other on-line tools securely across corporate, institutional, and
        geographic boundaries without sacrificing local autonomy.</para>

        <para>See Globus Toolkit</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Globus Toolkit</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Globus Toolkit is an open source software toolkit used for
        building Grid systems and applications.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>GRAM</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A Globus service that enable users to locate, submit, monitor
        and cancel remote jobs on Grid-based compute resources. It provides a
        single protocol for communicating with different batch/cluster job
        schedulers.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Grid</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A collection of many compute resources , each under different
        administrative domains connected via a network (usually the
        Internet).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>GridFTP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A high-performance, secure, reliable data transfer protocol
        optimized for high-bandwidth wide-area networks. It is based upon the
        Internet FTP protocol, and uses basic Grid security on both control
        (command) and data channels.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Grid Service</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A service which uses standardized web service mechanisms to
        model and access stateful resources, perform lifecycle management and
        query resource state. The Globus Toolkit includes core grid services
        for execution management, data management and information
        management.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>L</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Logical File Name</glossterm>

      <abbrev>LFN</abbrev>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The unique logical identifier for a data file. Each LFN is
        associated with a set of PFN’s that are the physical instantiations of
        the file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>M</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Metadata</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Any attributes of a dataset that are explicitly represented in
        the workflow system. These may include provenance information (e.g.,
        which component was used to generate the dataset), execution
        information (e.g., time of creation of the dataset), and properties of
        the dataset (e.g., density of a node type).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Monitoring and Discovery Service</glossterm>

      <abbrev>MDS</abbrev>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A Globus service that implements a site catalog.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>P</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Physical File Name</glossterm>

      <abbrev>PFN</abbrev>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The physical file name of the LFN.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Partitioner</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A tool in Pegasus that slices up the DAX into smaller DAX’s for
        deferred planning.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Pegasus</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A system that maps a workflow instance into an executable
        workflow to run on the grid.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>R</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Replica Catalog</glossterm>

      <abbrev>RC</abbrev>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A catalog that maps logical file names on to physical file
        names.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Replica Location Service</glossterm>

      <abbrev>RLS</abbrev>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A Globus service that implements a replica catalog</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>S</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Site</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A set of compute resources under a single administrative
        domain.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Site Catalog</glossterm>

      <abbrev>SC</abbrev>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A catalog indexed by logical site identifiers that maintains
        information about the various grid sites. The site catalog can be
        populated from a static database or maybe populated dynamically by
        monitoring tools.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>T</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Transformation</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Any executable or code that is run as a task in the
        workflow.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Transformation Catalog</glossterm>

      <abbrev>TC</abbrev>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A catalog that maps transformation names onto the physical
        pathnames of the transformation at a given grid site or local test
        machine.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>W</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Workflow Instance</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A workflow created in Wings and given to Pegasus in which
        workflow components and files are represented as logical names. It is
        an execution-independent specification of computations</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>