<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction to Pegasus</title>

  <para>Pegasus (<link xlink:href="http://pegasus.isi.edu"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://pegasus.isi.edu</link>) is a
  configurable system for mapping and executing abstract application workflows
  over the Grid.</para>

  <para>An abstract application workflow is represented as a directed acyclic
  graph where the vertices are the compute tasks and the edges represent the
  data dependencies between the tasks. The input to Pegasus is a description
  of the abstract workflow in XML format. The mapping of tasks to the
  execution resources is done based on information derived for static and/or
  dynamic sources (site catalog, transformation catalog, MDS (<link
  xlink:href="http://www.globus.org/toolkit/mds"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.globus.org/toolkit/mds/</link>)
  RLS (<link xlink:href="www.globus.org/toolkit/rls"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.globus.org/toolkit/rls</link>),
  etc).</para>

  <para>The output is an executable workflow (also called the concrete
  workflow) that can be executed over the Grid resources. In case the workflow
  tasks are mapped to multiple resources that do not share a file system,
  explicit nodes are added to the workflow for orchestrating data transfer
  between the tasks. The format of the concrete workflow is determined by the
  execution engine used for executing the concrete workflow over the mapped
  resources. For example, if Condor DAGMan <link
  xlink:href="http://cs.wisc.edu/condor/dagman"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">(http://cs.wisc.edu/condor/dagman)</link>
  is used as the enactment engine, then the concrete workflow consists of a
  DAG description file which lists the dependencies and Condor submit files
  for each task in the concrete workflow. Pegasus has been mostly used with
  Condor DAGMan. DAGMan can schedule jobs onto Globus (<link
  xlink:href="www,globus.org"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.globus.org</link>) and Condor
  (<link xlink:href="http://cs.wisc.edu/condor"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cs.wisc.edu/condor</link>)-managed
  resources. Condor-G can be used to execute any task in the workflow on any
  Grid resource that provides a Globus GRAM interface. The purpose of this
  document is to give an overview of the various resource configurations that
  can be used with Pegasus when Condor DAGMan is used as the workflow
  enactment engine. The classification is done based on the mechanism used for
  submitting jobs to these resources.</para>
</chapter>
