<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="tutorial">
  <title>Tutorial</title>

  <section id="tutorial_introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This tutorial will take you through the steps of running simple
    workflows using Pegasus Workflow Management System. Pegasus allows
    scientists to</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Automate</emphasis> their scientific
        computational work, as portable workflows. Pegasus enables scientists
        to construct workflows in abstract terms without worrying about the
        details of the underlying execution environment or the particulars of
        the low-level specifications required by the middleware (Condor,
        Globus, or Amazon EC2). It automatically locates the necessary input
        data and computational resources necessary for workflow execution. It
        cleans up storage as the workflow is executed so that data-intensive
        workflows have enough space to execute on storage-constrained
        resources.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Recover</emphasis> from failures at
        runtime. When errors occur, Pegasus tries to recover when possible by
        retrying tasks, and when all else fails, provides a rescue workflow
        containing a description of only the work that remains to be done. It
        also enables users to move computations from one resource to another.
        Pegasus keeps track of what has been done (provenance) including the
        locations of data used and produced, and which software was used with
        which parameters.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Debug</emphasis> failures in their
        computations using a set of system provided debugging tools and an
        online workflow monitoring dashboard.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>This tutorial is intended for new users who want to get a quick
    overview of Pegasus concepts and usage. The accompanying tutorial VM comes
    pre-configured to run the example workflows. The instructions listed here
    refer mainly to the simple split workflow example. The tutorial
    covers</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>submission of an already generated example workflow with
        Pegasus.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>how to use the Pegasus Workflow Dashboard for monitoring
        workflows.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the command line tools for monitoring, debugging and generating
        statistics.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>recovery from failures</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>creation of workflow using system provided API</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>information catalogs configuration.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>More information about the topics covered in this tutorial can be
    found in later chapters of this user's guide.</para>

    <para>All of the steps in this tutorial are performed on the command-line.
    The convention we will use for command-line input and output is to put
    things that you should type in bold, monospace font, and to put the output
    you should get in a normal weight, monospace font, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>[user@host dir]$ <emphasis role="bold">you type this</emphasis>
you get this</programlisting>

    <para>Where <literal>[user@host dir]$</literal> is the terminal prompt,
    the text you should type is “<literal>you type this</literal>”, and the
    output you should get is "<literal>you get this</literal>". The terminal
    prompt will be abbreviated as <literal>$</literal>. Because some of the
    outputs are long, we don’t always include everything. Where the output is
    truncated we will add an ellipsis '...' to indicate the omitted
    output.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">If you are having trouble with this tutorial,
    or anything else related to Pegasus, you can contact the Pegasus Users
    mailing list at <email>pegasus-users@isi.edu</email> to get help. You can
    also contact us on our <ulink
    url="https://pegasus.isi.edu/support">support chatroom</ulink> on HipChat.
    </emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_started">
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>Easiest way to start the tutorial is to connect to a hosted service
    using SSH as shown below.</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">ssh tutorial@pegasus-tutorial.isi.edu</emphasis>
tutorial@pegasus-tutorial.isi.edu's password: <emphasis role="bold">pegasus123</emphasis></programlisting>

    <para><note>
        <para>The workflow dashboard is not run in the hosted service. To try
        out the workflow dashboard use the virtual machines provided
        below.</para>
      </note></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">OR</emphasis></para>

    <para>We have provided several virtual machines that contain all of the
    software required for this tutorial. Virtual machine images are provided
    for <link linkend="vm_virtualbox">VirtualBox</link> and <link
    linkend="vm_amazon">Amazon EC2</link>. Information about deploying the
    tutorial VM on these platforms is in <link linkend="tutorial_vm">the
    appendix</link>. If you want to use the tutorial VM, please go to the
    appendix for the platform you are using and follow the instructions for
    starting the VM found there before continuing with this tutorial.</para>

    <para>If you have already installed Pegasus and Condor on your own
    machine, then you don't need to use the VM for the tutorial. You can use
    the <literal>pegasus-init</literal> command to generate the example
    workflow in any directory on your machine. Just be aware that you will
    have to modify the paths referenced in this tutorial to match the
    directory where you generated the example workflow.</para>

    <para>The remainder of this tutorial will assume that you have a terminal
    open with Pegasus on your PATH.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_scientific_workflows">
    <title>What are Scientific Workflows</title>

    <para>Scientific workflows allow users to easily express multi-step
    computational tasks, for example retrieve data from an instrument or a
    database, reformat the data, and run an analysis. A scientific workflow
    describes the dependencies between the tasks and in most cases the
    workflow is described as a directed acyclic graph (DAG), where the nodes
    are tasks and the edges denote the task dependencies. A defining property
    for a scientific workflow is that it manages data flow. The tasks in a
    scientific workflow can be everything from short serial tasks to very
    large parallel tasks (MPI for example) surrounded by a large number of
    small, serial tasks used for pre- and post-processing.</para>

    <para>Workflows can vary from simple to complex. Below are some examples.
    In the figures below, the task are designated by circles/ellipses while
    the files created by the tasks are indicated by rectangles. Arrows
    indicate task dependencies.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Process Workflow</emphasis></para>

    <para>It consists of a single task that runs the <literal>ls</literal>
    command and generates a listing of the files in the `/` directory.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Process Workflow</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="50%"
                     fileref="images/tutorial-single-job-wf.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Pipeline of Tasks</emphasis></para>

    <para>The pipeline workflow consists of two tasks linked together in a
    pipeline. The first job runs the `curl` command to fetch the Pegasus home
    page and store it as an HTML file. The result is passed to the `wc`
    command, which counts the number of lines in the HTML file. <figure>
        <title>Pipeline of Tasks</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="70%"
                       fileref="images/tutorial-pipeline-tasks-wf.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Split Workflow</emphasis></para>

    <para>The split workflow downloads the Pegasus home page using the `curl`
    command, then uses the `split` command to divide it into 4 pieces. The
    result is passed to the `wc` command to count the number of lines in each
    piece.<figure>
        <title>Split Workflow</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="70%"
                       fileref="images/tutorial-split-wf.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Merge Workflow</emphasis></para>

    <para>The merge workflow runs the `ls` command on several */bin
    directories and passes the results to the `cat` command, which merges the
    files into a single listing. The merge workflow is an example of a
    parameter sweep over arguments.<figure>
        <title>Merge Workflow</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="70%"
                       fileref="images/tutorial-merge-wf.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Diamond Workflow</emphasis></para>

    <para>The diamond workflow runs combines the split and merge workflow
    patterns to create a more complex workflow.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Diamond Workflow</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="70%"
                     fileref="images/tutorial-diamond-wf.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Complex Workflows</emphasis></para>

    <para>The above examples can be used as building blocks for much complex
    workflows. Some of these are showcased on the <ulink
    url="https://pegasus.isi.edu/applications">Pegasus Applications
    page</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_submitting_wf">
    <title>Submitting an Example Workflow</title>

    <para>All of the example workflows described in the previous section can
    be generated with the <literal>pegasus-init</literal> command. For this
    tutorial we will be using the split workflow, which can be created like
    this:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">cd /home/tutorial</emphasis>
$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-init split</emphasis>
Do you want to generate a tutorial workflow? (y/n) [n]: <emphasis role="bold">y</emphasis>
1: Process
2: Pipeline
3: Split
4: Merge
5: Diamond
What tutorial workflow do you want? (1-5) [1]: <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
$ <emphasis role="bold">cd split</emphasis>
$ <emphasis role="bold">ls</emphasis>
README.md          input              plan_dax.sh        tc.txt
daxgen.py          output             rc.txt
generate_dax.sh    pegasus.properties sites.xml
</programlisting>

    <tip>
      <para>The <literal>pegasus-init</literal> tool can be used to generate
      workflow skeletons from templates by asking the user questions. It is
      easier to use pegasus-init than to start a new workflow from
      scratch.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>The split workflow looks like this:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Split Workflow</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="70%"
                     fileref="images/tutorial-split-wf.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The input workflow description for Pegasus is called the DAX. It can
    be generated by running the <filename>generate_dax.sh</filename> script
    from the split directory, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">./generate_dax.sh split.dax</emphasis>
Generated dax split.dax
    </programlisting>

    <para>This script will run a small Python program
    (<filename>daxgen.py</filename>) that generates a file with a .dax
    extension using the Pegasus Python API. We will cover the details of
    creating a DAX programmatically <link
    linkend="tutorial_wf_generation">later in the tutorial</link>. Pegasus
    reads the DAX and generates an executable HTCondor workflow that is run on
    an execution site.</para>

    <para>The <literal>pegasus-plan</literal> command is used to submit the
    workflow through Pegasus. The pegasus-plan command reads the input
    workflow (DAX file specified by --dax option), maps the abstract DAX to
    one or more execution sites, and submits the generated executable workflow
    to HTCondor. Among other things, the options to pegasus-plan tell
    Pegasus</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the workflow to run</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>where (what site) to run the workflow</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the input directory where the inputs are placed</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the output directory where the outputs are placed</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>By default, the workflow is setup to run on the compute sites (i.e
    sites with handle other than "local") defined in the sites.xml file. In
    our example, the workflow will run on a site named "condorpool" in the
    sites.xml file.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If there are multiple compute sites specified in your sites.xml,
      and you want to choose a specific site, use the --sites option to
      pegasus-plan</para>
    </note>

    <para>To plan the split workflow invoke the pegasus-plan command using the
    <filename>plan_dax.sh</filename> wrapper script as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">./plan_dax.sh split.dax</emphasis>
2015.10.22 19:12:10.402 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:10.409 PDT:   -----------------------------------------------------------------------
2015.10.22 19:12:10.414 PDT:   File for submitting this DAG to Condor           : split-0.dag.condor.sub
2015.10.22 19:12:10.420 PDT:   Log of DAGMan debugging messages                 : split-0.dag.dagman.out
2015.10.22 19:12:10.426 PDT:   Log of Condor library output                     : split-0.dag.lib.out
2015.10.22 19:12:10.431 PDT:   Log of Condor library error messages             : split-0.dag.lib.err
2015.10.22 19:12:10.436 PDT:   Log of the life of condor_dagman itself          : split-0.dag.dagman.log
2015.10.22 19:12:10.442 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:10.458 PDT:   -----------------------------------------------------------------------
2015.10.22 19:12:14.292 PDT:   Your database is compatible with Pegasus version: 4.5.3
2015.10.22 19:12:15.198 PDT:   Submitting to condor split-0.dag.condor.sub
2015.10.22 19:12:15.997 PDT:   Submitting job(s).
2015.10.22 19:12:16.003 PDT:   1 job(s) submitted to cluster 111.
2015.10.22 19:12:16.035 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:16.055 PDT:   Your workflow has been started and is running in the base directory:
2015.10.22 19:12:16.061 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:16.071 PDT:     /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001
2015.10.22 19:12:16.078 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:16.084 PDT:   *** To monitor the workflow you can run ***
2015.10.22 19:12:16.090 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:16.098 PDT:     pegasus-status -l /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001
2015.10.22 19:12:16.114 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:16.119 PDT:   *** To remove your workflow run ***
2015.10.22 19:12:16.125 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:16.131 PDT:     pegasus-remove /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001
2015.10.22 19:12:16.137 PDT:
2015.10.22 19:12:17.630 PDT:   Time taken to execute is 1.918 seconds</programlisting>

    <note>
      <para>The line in the output that starts with
      <literal>pegasus-status</literal>, contains the command you can use to
      monitor the status of the workflow. The path it contains is the path to
      the submit directory where all of the files required to submit and
      monitor the workflow are stored.</para>
    </note>

    <para>This is what the split workflow looks like after Pegasus has
    finished planning the DAX:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Split DAG</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-split-dag.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>For this workflow the only jobs Pegasus needs to add are a directory
    creation job, a stage-in job (for pegasus.html), and stage-out jobs (for
    wc count outputs). The cleanup jobs remove data that is no longer required
    as workflow executes.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_wf_dashboard">
    <title>Workflow Dashboard for Monitoring and Debugging</title>

    <para>The Pegasus Dashboard is a web interface for monitoring and
    debugging workflows. We will use the web dashboard to monitor the status
    of the split workflow.</para>

    <para>If you are doing the tutorial using the tutorial VM, then the
    dashboard will start when the VM boots. If you are using your own machine,
    then you will need to start the dashboard by running:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-service</emphasis>
    </programlisting>

    <para>By default, the dashboard server can only monitor workflows run by
    the current user i.e. the user who is running the pegasus-service.</para>

    <para>Access the dashboard by navigating your browser to <emphasis
    role="bold">https://localhost:5000</emphasis>. If you are using the EC2 VM
    you will need to replace 'localhost' with the IP address of your EC2
    instance.</para>

    <para>When the webpage loads up, it will ask you for a username and a
    password. If you are using the tutorial VM, then log in as user "<emphasis
    role="bold">tutorial</emphasis>" with password "<emphasis
    role="bold">pegasus</emphasis>". If you are running the dashboard on your
    own machine, then use your UNIX username and password to log in.</para>

    <para>The Dashboard's home page lists all workflows, which have been run
    by the current-user. The home page shows the status of each workflow i.e.
    Running/Successful/Failed/Failing. The home page lists only the top level
    workflows (Pegasus supports hierarchical workflows i.e. workflows within a
    workflow). The rows in the table are color coded</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Green</emphasis>: indicates workflow
        finished successfully.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Red</emphasis>: indicates workflow
        finished with a failure.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Blue</emphasis>: indicates a workflow is
        currently running.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Gray</emphasis>: indicates a workflow that
        was archived.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Dashboard Home Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dashboard_home.png" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To view details specific to a workflow, the user can click on
    corresponding workflow label. The workflow details page lists workflow
    specific information like workflow label, workflow status, location of the
    submit directory, etc. The details page also displays pie charts showing
    the distribution of jobs based on status.</para>

    <para>In addition, the details page displays a tab listing all
    sub-workflows and their statuses. Additional tabs exist which list
    information for all running, failed, successful, and failing jobs.</para>

    <para>The information displayed for a job depends on it's status. For
    example, the failed jobs tab displays the job name, exit code, links to
    available standard output, and standard error contents.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Dashboard Workflow Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dashboard_workflow_details.png"
                     width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To view details specific to a job the user can click on the
    corresponding job's job label. The job details page lists information
    relevant to a specific job. For example, the page lists information like
    job name, exit code, run time, etc.</para>

    <para>The job instance section of the job details page lists all attempts
    made to run the job i.e. if a job failed in its first attempt due to
    transient errors, but ran successfully when retried, the job instance
    section shows two entries; one for each attempt to run the job.</para>

    <para>The job details page also shows tab's for failed, and successful
    task invocations (Pegasus allows users to group multiple smaller task's
    into a single job i.e. a job may consist of one or more tasks)</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Dashboard Job Description Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dashboard_job_details.png" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The task invocation details page provides task specific information
    like task name, exit code, duration etc. Task details differ from job
    details, as they are more granular in nature.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Dashboard Invocation Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dashboard_invocation_details.png"
                     width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The dashboard also has web pages for workflow statistics and
    workflow charts, which graphically renders information provided by the
    pegasus-statistics and pegasus-plots command respectively.</para>

    <para>The Statistics page shows the following statistics.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Workflow level statistics</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Job breakdown statistics</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Job specific statistics</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Dashboard Statistics Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dashboard_statistics.png" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_monitoring_cmd_tools">
    <title>Command line tools for Monitoring and Debugging</title>

    <para>Pegasus also comes with a series of command line tools that users
    can use to monitor and debug their workflows.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>pegasus-status : monitor the status of the workflow</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>pegasus-analyzer : debug a failed workflow</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>pegasus-statistics : generate statistics from a workflow
        run.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>pegasus-status - monitoring the workflow</title>

      <para>After the workflow has been submitted you can monitor it using the
      <literal>pegasus-status</literal> command:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-status -l submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001</emphasis>
STAT  IN_STATE  JOB
Run      00:39  split-0 ( /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001 )
Idle     00:03   ┗━split_ID0000001
Summary: 2 Condor jobs total (I:1 R:1)

UNRDY READY   PRE  IN_Q  POST  DONE  FAIL %DONE STATE   DAGNAME
   14     0     0     1     0     2     0  11.8 Running *split-0.dag     </programlisting>

      <para>This command shows the workflow (split-0) and the running jobs (in
      the above output it shows the two findrange jobs). It also gives
      statistics on the number of jobs in each state and the percentage of the
      jobs in the workflow that have finished successfully.</para>

      <para>Use the <literal>watch</literal> option to continuously monitor
      the workflow:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-status -w submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001</emphasis>
...</programlisting>

      <para>You should see all of the jobs in the workflow run one after the
      other. After a few minutes you will see:</para>

      <programlisting>(no matching jobs found in Condor Q)
UNRDY READY   PRE  IN_Q  POST  DONE  FAIL %DONE STATE   DAGNAME
    0     0     0     0     0    15     0 100.0 Success *split-0.dag      </programlisting>

      <para>That means the workflow is finished successfully.</para>

      <para>If the workflow finished successfully you should see the output
      count files in the <filename>output</filename> directory.</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">ls output/</emphasis>
count.txt.a  count.txt.b  count.txt.c  count.txt.d
</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>pegasus-analyzer - debug a failed workflow</title>

      <para>In the case that one or more jobs fails, then the output of the
      <literal>pegasus-status</literal> command above will have a non-zero
      value in the <literal>FAILURE</literal> column.</para>

      <para>You can debug the failure using the
      <literal>pegasus-analyzer</literal> command. This command will identify
      the jobs that failed and show their output. Because the workflow
      succeeded, <literal>pegasus-analyzer</literal> will only show some basic
      statistics about the number of successful jobs:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-analyzer submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001</emphasis>
pegasus-analyzer: initializing...

****************************Summary***************************

 Total jobs         :      11 (100.00%)
 # jobs succeeded   :      11 (100.00%)
 # jobs failed      :      0 (0.00%)
 # jobs unsubmitted :      0 (0.00%)
</programlisting>

      <para>If the workflow had failed you would see something like
      this:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-analyzer submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002</emphasis>

************************************Summary*************************************

 Submit Directory   : submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002
 Total jobs         :     15 (100.00%)
 # jobs succeeded   :      1 (5.88%)
 # jobs failed      :      1 (5.88%)
 # jobs unsubmitted :     15 (88.24%)

******************************Failed jobs' details******************************

==========================stage_in_local_PegasusVM_0_0==========================

 last state: POST_SCRIPT_FAILED
       site: local
submit file: stage_in_local_PegasusVM_0_0.sub
output file: stage_in_local_PegasusVM_0_0.out.001
 error file: stage_in_local_PegasusVM_0_0.err.001

-------------------------------Task #1 - Summary--------------------------------

site        : local
hostname    : unknown
executable  : /usr/bin/pegasus-transfer
arguments   :   --threads   2
exitcode    : 1
working dir : /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002

------------------Task #1 - pegasus::transfer - None - stdout-------------------

2015-10-22 21:13:50,970    INFO:  Reading URL pairs from stdin
2015-10-22 21:13:50,970    INFO:  PATH=/usr/bin:/bin
2015-10-22 21:13:50,970    INFO:  LD_LIBRARY_PATH=
2015-10-22 21:13:50,972    INFO:  1 transfers loaded
2015-10-22 21:13:50,972    INFO:  Sorting the tranfers based on transfer type and source/destination
2015-10-22 21:13:50,972    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2015-10-22 21:13:50,972    INFO:  Starting transfers - attempt 1
2015-10-22 21:13:50,972    INFO:  Using 1 threads for this round of transfers
2015-10-22 21:13:53,845   ERROR:  Command exited with non-zero exit code (1): /usr/bin/scp -r -B -o UserKnownHostsFile=/dev/null -o StrictHostKeyChecking=no -i /home/tutorial/.ssh/id_rsa -P 22 '/home/tutorial/examples/split/input/pegasus.html' 'tutorial@127.0.0.1:/home/tutorial/work/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/pegasus.html'
2015-10-22 21:15:55,911    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2015-10-22 21:15:55,912    INFO:  Starting transfers - attempt 2
2015-10-22 21:15:55,912    INFO:  Using 1 threads for this round of transfers
2015-10-22 21:15:58,446   ERROR:  Command exited with non-zero exit code (1): /usr/bin/scp -r -B -o UserKnownHostsFile=/dev/null -o StrictHostKeyChecking=no -i /home/tutorial/.ssh/id_rsa -P 22 '/home/tutorial/examples/split/input/pegasus.html' 'tutorial@127.0.0.1:/home/tutorial/work/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/pegasus.html'
2015-10-22 21:16:40,468    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2015-10-22 21:16:40,469    INFO:  Starting transfers - attempt 3
2015-10-22 21:16:40,469    INFO:  Using 1 threads for this round of transfers
2015-10-22 21:16:43,168   ERROR:  Command exited with non-zero exit code (1): /usr/bin/scp -r -B -o UserKnownHostsFile=/dev/null -o StrictHostKeyChecking=no -i /home/tutorial/.ssh/id_rsa -P 22 '/home/tutorial/examples/split/input/pegasus.html' 'tutorial@127.0.0.1:/home/tutorial/work/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/pegasus.html'
2015-10-22 21:16:43,173    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2015-10-22 21:16:43,173    INFO:  Stats: no local files in the transfer set
2015-10-22 21:16:43,173 CRITICAL:  Some transfers failed! See above, and possibly stderr.


-------------Task #1 - pegasus::transfer - None - Kickstart stderr--------------

Warning: Permanently added '127.0.0.1' (RSA) to the list of known hosts.<emphasis
          role="bold">
/home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html: No such file or directory</emphasis>
..
<emphasis role="bold">/home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html: No such file or directory
</emphasis></programlisting>

      <para>In this example, we removed one of the input files. We will cover
      this in more detail in the recovery section. The output of
      <literal>pegasus-analyzer</literal> indicates that pegasus.html file
      could not be found.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>pegasus-statistics - collect statistics about a workflow
      run</title>

      <para>The <literal>pegasus-statistics</literal> command can be used to
      gather statistics about the runtime of the workflow and its jobs. The
      <literal>-s all</literal> argument tells the program to generate all
      statistics it knows how to calculate:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-statistics –s all submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001</emphasis>

#
# Pegasus Workflow Management System - http://pegasus.isi.edu
#
# Workflow summary:
#   Summary of the workflow execution. It shows total
#   tasks/jobs/sub workflows run, how many succeeded/failed etc.
#   In case of hierarchical workflow the calculation shows the
#   statistics across all the sub workflows.It shows the following
#   statistics about tasks, jobs and sub workflows.
#     * Succeeded - total count of succeeded tasks/jobs/sub workflows.
#     * Failed - total count of failed tasks/jobs/sub workflows.
#     * Incomplete - total count of tasks/jobs/sub workflows that are
#       not in succeeded or failed state. This includes all the jobs
#       that are not submitted, submitted but not completed etc. This
#       is calculated as  difference between 'total' count and sum of
#       'succeeded' and 'failed' count.
#     * Total - total count of tasks/jobs/sub workflows.
#     * Retries - total retry count of tasks/jobs/sub workflows.
#     * Total+Retries - total count of tasks/jobs/sub workflows executed
#       during workflow run. This is the cumulative of retries,
#       succeeded and failed count.
# Workflow wall time:
#   The wall time from the start of the workflow execution to the end as
#   reported by the DAGMAN.In case of rescue dag the value is the
#   cumulative of all retries.
# Workflow cumulative job wall time:
#   The sum of the wall time of all jobs as reported by kickstart.
#   In case of job retries the value is the cumulative of all retries.
#   For workflows having sub workflow jobs (i.e SUBDAG and SUBDAX jobs),
#   the wall time value includes jobs from the sub workflows as well.
# Cumulative job wall time as seen from submit side:
#   The sum of the wall time of all jobs as reported by DAGMan.
#   This is similar to the regular cumulative job wall time, but includes
#   job management overhead and delays. In case of job retries the value
#   is the cumulative of all retries. For workflows having sub workflow
#   jobs (i.e SUBDAG and SUBDAX jobs), the wall time value includes jobs
#   from the sub workflows as well.
# Cumulative job wall time as seen from submit side:
#   The sum of the wall time of all jobs as reported by DAGMan.
#   This is similar to the regular cumulative job wall time, but includes
#   job management overhead and delays. In case of job retries the value
#   is the cumulative of all retries. For workflows having sub workflow
#   jobs (i.e SUBDAG and SUBDAX jobs), the wall time value includes jobs
#   from the sub workflows as well.
# Workflow cumulative job badput wall time:
#   The sum of the wall time of all failed jobs as reported by kickstart.
#   In case of job retries the value is the cumulative of all retries.
#   For workflows having sub workflow jobs (i.e SUBDAG and SUBDAX jobs),
#   the wall time value includes jobs from the sub workflows as well.
# Cumulative job badput wall time as seen from submit side:
#   The sum of the wall time of all failed jobs as reported by DAGMan.
#   This is similar to the regular cumulative job badput wall time, but includes
#   job management overhead and delays. In case of job retries the value
#   is the cumulative of all retries. For workflows having sub workflow
#   jobs (i.e SUBDAG and SUBDAX jobs), the wall time value includes jobs
#   from the sub workflows as well.

------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Type           Succeeded Failed  Incomplete  Total     Retries   Total+Retries
Tasks          5         0       0           5         0         5
Jobs           15        0       0           15        0         15
Sub-Workflows  0         0       0           0         0         0
------------------------------------------------------------------------------

Workflow wall time                                       : 2 mins, 6 secs
Workflow cumulative job wall time                        : 38 secs
Cumulative job wall time as seen from submit side        : 42 secs
Workflow cumulative job badput wall time                 :
Cumulative job badput wall time as seen from submit side :

Summary                       : submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001/statistics/summary.txt
Workflow execution statistics : submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001/statistics/workflow.txt
Job instance statistics       : submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001/statistics/jobs.txt
Transformation statistics     : submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001/statistics/breakdown.txt
Time statistics               : submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001/statistics/time.txt


</programlisting>

      <para>The output of <literal>pegasus-statistics</literal> contains many
      definitions to help users understand what all of the values reported
      mean. Among these are the total wall time of the workflow, which is the
      time from when the workflow was submitted until it finished, and the
      total cumulative job wall time, which is the sum of the runtimes of all
      the jobs.</para>

      <para>The <literal>pegasus-statistics</literal> command also writes out
      several reports in the <filename>statistics</filename> subdirectory of
      the workflow submit directory:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">ls submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001/statistics/</emphasis>
jobs.txt          summary.txt         time.txt          breakdown.txt          workflow.txt</programlisting>

      <para>The file <filename>breakdown.txt</filename>, for example, has min,
      max, and mean runtimes for each transformation:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">more submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0001/statistics/breakdown.txt</emphasis>
# legends
# Transformation - name of the transformation.
# Count          - the number of times the invocations corresponding to
#                  the transformation was executed.
# Succeeded      - the count of the succeeded invocations corresponding
#                  to the transformation.
# Failed         - the count of the failed invocations corresponding to
#                  the transformation.
# Min(sec)       - the minimum invocation runtime value corresponding to
#                  the transformation.
# Max(sec)       - the maximum invocation runtime value corresponding to
#                  the transformation.
# Mean(sec)      - the mean of the invocation runtime corresponding to
#                  the transformation.
# Total(sec)     - the cumulative of invocation runtime corresponding to
#                  the transformation.

# 773d8fa3-8bff-4f75-8e2b-38e2c904f803 (split)
Transformation           Count     Succeeded Failed  Min       Max       Mean      Total
dagman::post             15        15        0       5.0       6.0       5.412     92.0
pegasus::cleanup         6         6         0       1.474     3.178     2.001     12.008
pegasus::dirmanager      1         1         0       2.405     2.405     2.405     2.405
pegasus::rc-client       2         2         0       2.382     7.406     4.894     9.788
pegasus::transfer        3         3         0       3.951     5.21      4.786     14.358
split                    1         1         0       0.009     0.009     0.009     0.009
wc                       4         4         0       0.005     0.029     0.012     0.047


# All (All)
Transformation           Count     Succeeded  Failed  Min       Max       Mean      Total
dagman::post             15        15         0       5.0       6.0       5.412     92.0
pegasus::cleanup         6         6          0       1.474     3.178     2.001     12.008
pegasus::dirmanager      1         1          0       2.405     2.405     2.405     2.405
pegasus::rc-client       2         2          0       2.382     7.406     4.894     9.788
pegasus::transfer        3         3          0       3.951     5.21      4.786     14.358
split                    1         1          0       0.009     0.009     0.009     0.009
wc                       4         4          0       0.005     0.029     0.012     0.047
</programlisting>

      <para>In this case, because the example transformation sleeps for 30
      seconds, the min, mean, and max runtimes for each of the analyze,
      findrange, and preprocess transformations are all close to 30.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_failure_recovery">
    <title>Recovery from Failures</title>

    <para>Executing workflows in a distributed environment can lead to
    failures. Often, they are a result of the underlying infrastructure being
    temporarily unavailable, or errors in workflow setup such as incorrect
    executables specified, or input files being unavailable.</para>

    <para>In case of transient infrastructure failures such as a node being
    temporarily down in a cluster, Pegasus will automatically retry jobs in
    case of failure. After a set number of retries (usually once), a hard
    failure occurs, because of which workflow will eventually fail.</para>

    <para>In most of the cases, these errors are correctable (either the
    resource comes back online or application errors are fixed). Once the
    errors are fixed, you may not want to start a new workflow but instead
    start from the point of failure. In order to do this, you can submit the
    rescue workflows automatically created in case of failures. A rescue
    workflow contains only a description of only the work that remains to be
    done.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Submitting Rescue Workflows</title>

      <para>In this example, we will take our previously run workflow and
      introduce errors such that workflow we just executed fails at
      runtime.</para>

      <para>First we will "hide" the input file to cause a failure by renaming
      it:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">mv input/pegasus.html input/pegasus.html.bak</emphasis>
      </programlisting>

      <para>Now submit the workflow again:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">./plan_dax.sh split.dax</emphasis>
2015.10.22 20:20:08.299 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:08.307 PDT:   -----------------------------------------------------------------------
2015.10.22 20:20:08.312 PDT:   File for submitting this DAG to Condor           : split-0.dag.condor.sub
2015.10.22 20:20:08.323 PDT:   Log of DAGMan debugging messages                 : split-0.dag.dagman.out
2015.10.22 20:20:08.330 PDT:   Log of Condor library output                     : split-0.dag.lib.out
2015.10.22 20:20:08.339 PDT:   Log of Condor library error messages             : split-0.dag.lib.err
2015.10.22 20:20:08.346 PDT:   Log of the life of condor_dagman itself          : split-0.dag.dagman.log
2015.10.22 20:20:08.352 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:08.368 PDT:   -----------------------------------------------------------------------
2015.10.22 20:20:12.331 PDT:   Your database is compatible with Pegasus version: 4.5.3
2015.10.22 20:20:13.326 PDT:   Submitting to condor split-0.dag.condor.sub
2015.10.22 20:20:14.224 PDT:   Submitting job(s).
2015.10.22 20:20:14.254 PDT:   1 job(s) submitted to cluster 168.
2015.10.22 20:20:14.288 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:14.297 PDT:   Your workflow has been started and is running in the base directory:
2015.10.22 20:20:14.303 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:14.309 PDT:     /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002
2015.10.22 20:20:14.315 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:14.321 PDT:   *** To monitor the workflow you can run ***
2015.10.22 20:20:14.326 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:14.332 PDT:     pegasus-status -l /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002
2015.10.22 20:20:14.351 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:14.369 PDT:   *** To remove your workflow run ***
2015.10.22 20:20:14.376 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:14.388 PDT:     pegasus-remove /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002
2015.10.22 20:20:14.397 PDT:
2015.10.22 20:20:16.146 PDT:   Time taken to execute is 10.292 seconds
</programlisting>

      <para>We will now monitor the workflow using the pegasus-status command
      till it fails. We will add -w option to pegasus-status to watch
      automatically till the workflow finishes:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">$ </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">pegasus-status -w submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002</emphasis>
(no matching jobs found in Condor Q)
UNREADY   READY     PRE  QUEUED    POST SUCCESS FAILURE %DONE
      8       0       0       0       0       2       1  18.2
Summary: 1 DAG total (Failure:1)
</programlisting>

      <para>Now we can use the pegasus-analyzer command to determine what went
      wrong:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">$ </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">pegasus-analyzer submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002</emphasis>

************************************Summary*************************************

 Submit Directory   : submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002
 Total jobs         :     11 (100.00%)
 # jobs succeeded   :      2 (18.18%)
 # jobs failed      :      1 (9.09%)
 # jobs unsubmitted :      8 (72.73%)

******************************Failed jobs' details******************************

===========================stage_in_remote_local_0_0============================

 last state: POST_SCRIPT_FAILED
       site: local
submit file: stage_in_remote_local_0_0.sub
output file: stage_in_remote_local_0_0.out.001
 error file: stage_in_remote_local_0_0.err.001

-------------------------------Task #1 - Summary--------------------------------

site        : local
hostname    : unknown
executable  : /usr/local/bin/pegasus-transfer
arguments   :   --threads   2
exitcode    : 1
working dir : /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002

------------------Task #1 - pegasus::transfer - None - stdout-------------------

2016-02-18 11:52:58,189    INFO:  Reading URL pairs from stdin
2016-02-18 11:52:58,189    INFO:  PATH=/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin
2016-02-18 11:52:58,189    INFO:  LD_LIBRARY_PATH=
2016-02-18 11:52:58,189    INFO:  1 transfers loaded
2016-02-18 11:52:58,189    INFO:  Sorting the tranfers based on transfer type and source/destination
2016-02-18 11:52:58,190    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2016-02-18 11:52:58,190    INFO:  Starting transfers - attempt 1
2016-02-18 11:52:58,190    INFO:  Using 1 threads for this round of transfers
2016-02-18 11:53:00,205   ERROR:  Command exited with non-zero exit code (1): /bin/cp -f -R -L '/home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html' '/home/tutorial/split/scratch/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/pegasus.html'
2016-02-18 11:54:46,205    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2016-02-18 11:54:46,205    INFO:  Starting transfers - attempt 2
2016-02-18 11:54:46,205    INFO:  Using 1 threads for this round of transfers
2016-02-18 11:54:48,220   ERROR:  Command exited with non-zero exit code (1): /bin/cp -f -R -L '/home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html' '/home/tutorial/split/scratch/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/pegasus.html'
2016-02-18 11:55:24,224    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2016-02-18 11:55:24,224    INFO:  Starting transfers - attempt 3
2016-02-18 11:55:24,224    INFO:  Using 1 threads for this round of transfers
2016-02-18 11:55:26,240   ERROR:  Command exited with non-zero exit code (1): /bin/cp -f -R -L '/home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html' '/home/tutorial/split/scratch/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/pegasus.html'
2016-02-18 11:55:26,240    INFO:  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------
2016-02-18 11:55:26,240    INFO:  Stats: no local files in the transfer set
2016-02-18 11:55:26,240 CRITICAL:  Some transfers failed! See above, and possibly stderr.


-------------Task #1 - pegasus::transfer - None - Kickstart stderr--------------

cp: /home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html: No such file or directory
cp: /home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html: No such file or directory
cp: /home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html: No such file or directory
</programlisting>

      <para>The above listing indicates that it could not transfer
      pegasus.html. Let's correct that error by restoring the pegasus.html
      file:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">mv input/pegasus.html.bak input/pegasus.html</emphasis>
      </programlisting>

      <para>Now in order to start the workflow from where we left off, instead
      of executing pegasus-plan we will use the command pegasus-run on the
      directory from our previous failed workflow run:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">pegasus-run submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/</emphasis>
Rescued /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/split-0.log as /home/tutorial/split/submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/split-0.log.000
Submitting to condor split-0.dag.condor.sub
Submitting job(s).
1 job(s) submitted to cluster 181.

Your workflow has been started and is running in the base directory:

  submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/

*** To monitor the workflow you can run ***

  pegasus-status -l submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/

*** To remove your workflow run ***

  pegasus-remove submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/
</programlisting>

      <para>The workflow will now run to completion and succeed.</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">$ pegasus-status -l <emphasis
            role="bold">submit/tutorial/pegasus/split/run0002/</emphasis></emphasis>
(no matching jobs found in Condor Q)
UNRDY READY   PRE  IN_Q  POST  DONE  FAIL %DONE STATE   DAGNAME
    0     0     0     0     0    11     0 100.0 Success *split-0.dag
Summary: 1 DAG total (Success:1)

</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_wf_generation">
    <title>Generating the Workflow</title>

    <para>The example that you ran earlier already had the workflow
    description (split.dax) generated. Pegasus reads workflow descriptions
    from DAX files. The term "DAX" is short for "Directed Acyclic Graph in
    XML". DAX is an XML file format that has syntax for expressing jobs,
    arguments, files, and dependencies. We now will be creating the split
    workflow that we just ran using the Pegasus provided DAX API:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Split Workflow</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="70%"
                     fileref="images/tutorial-split-wf.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In this diagram, the ovals represent computational jobs, the
    dog-eared squares are files, and the arrows are dependencies.</para>

    <para>In order to create a DAX it is necessary to write code for a DAX
    generator. Pegasus comes with Perl, Java, and Python libraries for writing
    DAX generators. In this tutorial we will show how to use the Python
    library.</para>

    <para>The DAX generator for the split workflow is in the file
    <filename>daxgen.py</filename>. Look at the file by typing:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">more daxgen.py</emphasis>
...</programlisting>

    <tip>
      <para>We will be using the <literal>more</literal> command to inspect
      several files in this tutorial. <literal>more</literal> is a pager
      application, meaning that it splits text files into pages and displays
      the pages one at a time. You can view the next page of a file by
      pressing the spacebar. Type 'h' to get help on using
      <literal>more</literal>. When you are done, you can type 'q' to close
      the file.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>The code has 3 main sections:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A new ADAG object is created. This is the main object to which
        jobs and dependencies are added.</para>

        <programlisting># Create a abstract dag
dax = ADAG("split")
...
</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Jobs and files are added. The 5 jobs in the diagram above are
        added and 9 files are referenced. Arguments are defined using strings
        and File objects. The input and output files are defined for each job.
        This is an important step, as it allows Pegasus to track the files,
        and stage the data if necessary. Workflow outputs are tagged with
        "transfer=true".</para>

        <programlisting># the split job that splits the webpage into smaller chunks
webpage = File("pegasus.html")

split = Job("split")
split.addArguments("-l","100","-a","1",webpage,"part.")
split.uses(webpage, link=Link.INPUT)
dax.addJob(split)

...
</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Dependencies are added. These are shown as arrows in the diagram
        above. They define the parent/child relationships between the jobs.
        When the workflow is executing, the order in which the jobs will be
        run is determined by the dependencies between them.</para>

        <programlisting># Add control-flow dependencies
dax.depends(wc, split)
</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Generate a DAX file named <filename>split.dax</filename> by
    typing:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">./generate_dax.sh </emphasis>split.dax
Generated dax split.dax</programlisting>

    <para>The <filename>split.dax</filename> file should contain an XML
    representation of the split workflow. You can inspect it by typing:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">more split.dax</emphasis>
...</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_catalogs">
    <title>Information Catalogs</title>

    <para>The workflow description (DAX) that you specify to Pegasus is
    portable, and usually does not contain any locations to physical input
    files, executables or cluster end points where jobs are executed. Pegasus
    uses three information catalogs during the planning process.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Information Catalogs used by Pegasus</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-pegasus-catalogs.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="tut_site_catalog">
      <title>The Site Catalog</title>

      <para>The site catalog describes the sites where the workflow jobs are
      to be executed. In this tutorial we assume that you have a Personal
      Condor pool running on localhost. If you are using one of the tutorial
      VMs this has already been setup for you. The site catalog for the
      tutorial examples is in <filename>sites.xml</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">more sites.xml</emphasis>
...
   &lt;!-- The local site contains information about the submit host --&gt;
    &lt;!-- The arch and os keywords are used to match binaries in the transformation catalog --&gt;
    &lt;site handle="local" arch="x86_64" os="LINUX"&gt;

        <emphasis role="bold">&lt;!-- These are the paths on the submit host were Pegasus stores data --&gt;
        &lt;!-- Scratch is where temporary files go --&gt;</emphasis>
        &lt;directory type="shared-scratch" path="/home/tutorial/scratch"&gt;
            &lt;file-server operation="all" url="file:///home/tutorial/scratch"/&gt;
        &lt;/directory&gt;

       <emphasis role="bold"> &lt;!-- Storage is where pegasus stores output files --&gt;</emphasis>
        &lt;directory type="local-storage" path="/home/tutorial/output"&gt;
            &lt;file-server operation="all" url="file:///home/tutorial/output"/&gt;
        &lt;/directory&gt;
    &lt;/site&gt;

...
      </programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>By default (unless specified in properties), Pegasus picks ups
        the site catalog from a XML file named sites.xml in the current
        working directory from where pegasus-plan is invoked.</para>
      </note>

      <para>There are two sites defined in the site catalog: "local" and
      "condorpool". The "local" site is used by Pegasus to learn about the
      submit host where the workflow management system runs. The "condorpool"
      site is the Condor pool configured on your submit machine. In the case
      of the tutorial VM, the local site and the condorpool site refer to the
      same machine, but they are logically separate as far as Pegasus is
      concerned.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">local</emphasis> site is configured
          with a "storage" file system that is mounted on the submit host
          (indicated by the file:// URL). This file system is where the output
          data from the workflow will be stored. When the workflow is planned
          we will tell Pegasus that the output site is "local".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">condorpool</emphasis> site is also
          configured with a "scratch" file system. This file system is where
          the working directory will be created. When we plan the workflow we
          will tell Pegasus that the execution site is "condorpool".</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Pegasus supports many different file transfer protocols. In this
      case the Pegasus configuration is set up so that input and output files
      are transferred to/from the condorpool site by Condor. This is done by
      setting <literal>pegasus.data.configuration = condorio</literal> in the
      properties file. In a normal Condor pool, this will cause job
      input/output files to be transferred from/to the submit host to/from the
      worker node. In the case of the tutorial VM, this configuration is just
      a fancy way to copy files from the workflow scratch directory to the job
      scratch directory.</para>

      <para>Finally, the condorpool site is configured with two profiles that
      tell Pegasus that it is a plain Condor pool. Pegasus supports many ways
      of submitting tasks to a remote cluster. In this configuration it will
      submit vanilla Condor jobs.</para>

      <section>
        <title>HPC Clusters</title>

        <para>Typically the sites in the site catalog describe remote
        clusters, such as PBS clusters or Condor pools.</para>

        <para>Usually, a typical deployment of an HPC cluster is illustrated
        below. The site catalog, captures for each cluster (site)</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>directories that can be used for executing jobs</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>whether a shared file system is available</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>file servers to use for staging input data and staging out
            output data</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>headnode of the cluster to which jobs can be
            submitted.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <figure>
          <title>Sample HPC Cluster Setup</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-hpc-cluster.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Below is a sample site catalog entry for HPC cluster at SDSC
        that is part of XSEDE</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;site  handle="sdsc-gordon" arch="x86_64" os="LINUX"&gt;
        &lt;grid  type="gt5" contact="gordon-ln4.sdsc.xsede.org:2119/jobmanager-fork" scheduler="Fork" jobtype="auxillary"/&gt;
        &lt;grid  type="gt5" contact="gordon-ln4.sdsc.xsede.org:2119/jobmanager-pbs" scheduler="unknown" jobtype="compute"/&gt;

        &lt;!-- the base directory where workflow jobs will execute for the site --&gt;
        &lt;directory type="shared-scratch" path="/oasis/scratch/ux454281/temp_project"&gt;
            &lt;file-server operation="all" url="gsiftp://oasis-dm.sdsc.xsede.org:2811/oasis/scratch/ux454281/temp_project"/&gt;
        &lt;/directory&gt;

        &lt;profile namespace="globus" key="project"&gt;TG-STA110014S&lt;/profile&gt;
        &lt;profile namespace="env" key="PEGASUS_HOME"&gt;/home/ux454281/software/pegasus/pegasus-4.5.0&lt;/profile&gt;
    &lt;/site&gt;</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title id="tut_xform_catalog">The Transformation Catalog</title>

      <para>The transformation catalog describes all of the executables
      (called "transformations") used by the workflow. This description
      includes the site(s) where they are located, the architecture and
      operating system they are compiled for, and any other information
      required to properly transfer them to the execution site and run
      them.</para>

      <para>For this tutorial, the transformation catalog is in the file
      <filename>tc.txt</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">more tc.txt</emphasis>
tr wc {
    site condorpool {
        pfn "/usr/bin/wc"
        arch "x86_64"
        os "linux"
        type "INSTALLED"
    }
}
...</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>By default (unless specified in properties), Pegasus picks up
        the transformation catalog from a text file named tc.txt in the
        current working directory from where pegasus-plan is invoked.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The <filename>tc.txt</filename> file contains information about
      two transformations: wc, and split. These two transformations are
      referenced in the split DAX. The transformation catalog indicates that
      both transformations are installed on the condorpool site, and are
      compiled for x86_64 Linux.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title id="tut_replica_catalog">The Replica Catalog</title>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> Replica Catalog
      configuration is not required for the tutorial setup. It is only
      required if you want to refer to input files on external servers.</para>

      <para>The example that you ran, was configured with the inputs already
      present on the submit host (where Pegasus is installed) in a directory.
      If you have inputs at external servers, then you can specify the URLs to
      the input files in the Replica Catalog. This catalog tells Pegasus where
      to find each of the input files for the workflow.</para>

      <para>All files in a Pegasus workflow are referred to in the DAX using
      their Logical File Name (LFN). These LFNs are mapped to Physical File
      Names (PFNs) when Pegasus plans the workflow. This level of indirection
      enables Pegasus to map abstract DAXes to different execution sites and
      plan out the required file transfers automatically.</para>

      <para>The Replica Catalog for the diamond workflow is in the
      <filename>rc.txt</filename> file:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">more rc.txt</emphasis>
# This is the replica catalog. It lists information about each of the
# input files used by the workflow. You can use this to specify locations to input files present on external servers.

# The format is:
# LFN     PFN    pool="SITE"
#
# For example:
#data.txt  file:///tmp/data.txt         site="local"
#data.txt  http://example.org/data.txt  site="example"
pegasus.html file:///home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html   site="local"
</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>By default (unless specified in properties), Pegasus picks ups
        the transformation catalog from a text file named tc.txt in the
        current working directory from where pegasus-plan is invoked. In our
        tutorial, input files are on the submit host and we used the --input
        dir option to pegasus-plan to specify where they are located.</para>
      </note>

      <para>This replica catalog contains only one entry for the split
      workflow’s only input file. This entry has an LFN of "pegasus.html" with
      a PFN of "file:///home/tutorial/split/input/pegasus.html" and the file
      is stored on the local site, which implies that it will need to be
      transferred to the condorpool site when the workflow runs.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_configuration">
    <title>Configuring Pegasus</title>

    <para>In addition to the information catalogs, Pegasus takes a
    configuration file that specifies settings that control how it plans the
    workflow.</para>

    <para>For the diamond workflow, the Pegasus configuration file is
    relatively simple. It only contains settings to help Pegasus find the
    information catalogs. These settings are in the
    <filename>pegasus.properties</filename> file:</para>

    <programlisting>$ <emphasis role="bold">more pegasus.properties</emphasis>
# This tells Pegasus where to find the Site Catalog
pegasus.catalog.site.file=sites.xml

# This tells Pegasus where to find the Replica Catalog
pegasus.catalog.replica=File
pegasus.catalog.replica.file=rc.txt

# This tells Pegasus where to find the Transformation Catalog
pegasus.catalog.transformation=Text
pegasus.catalog.transformation.file=tc.txt

# Use condor to transfer workflow data
pegasus.data.configuration=condorio

# This is the name of the application for analytics
pegasus.metrics.app=pegasus-tutorial
</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="tutorial_conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>Congratulations! You have completed the tutorial.</para>

    <para>If you used Amazon EC2 for this tutorial make sure to terminate your
    VM. Refer to the <link linkend="tutorial_vm">appendix</link> for more
    information about how to do this.</para>

    <para>Refer to the other chapters in this guide for more information about
    creating, planning, and executing workflows with Pegasus.</para>

    <para>Please contact the Pegasus Users Mailing list at
    <email>pegasus-users@isi.edu</email> if you need help.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
